Bill Vivino

Software Developer

http://www.github.com/billvivino https://billvivino.github.io

ABOUT

I currently work as a contract/freelance iOS developer for Upwork clients and a Unity/C# developer for an app for the NASA visitor center. I have four apps published on the App Store. In addition, I co-founded an iOS game startup company with one of my clients and code software under contract for many others. I am also in various consulting roles, helping develop iOS applications for small-sized firms and bringing multiple apps live on the App Store. Lastly, I work with youth as a general music teacher in a public school.

I have a B.S. in computer science from Rutgers University in 2004. After a long hiatus from coding, I returned as a contract/freelance software developer. I began my return by developing an app for craft beer lovers and creating a port of a Unity LEGO game from PC to iOS. These projects, in turn, led to completing iOS apps for multiple Upwork clients. My experience developing Unity/C# games for other clients and my iOS games helped lead to my current role with AMC/NASA. My future goal is to continue to expand my horizons, "making things work."

EXPERIENCE

Co-founder, SoulandForm, LLC (https://soulandform.com/) - Sole iOS Developer JAN 2022 - PRESENT

- You can download this app on the App Store at the following URL: https://apps.apple.com/us/app/soul-and form/id1633902006
- Built a SwiftUI-based animation video game with a Firebase backend for an Upwork client from scratch. This contract turned into a business partnership.
- I coded the app from scratch using SwiftUI and Firebase.
- Responsible for all UI and backend calls as well as Firebase security rules.
- Coded StoreKit functionality for in-app purchase subscriptions.
- Gameplay players draw animations and challenge other players to find out the "link" or "rule" between the animations.

All-Star Sports, Eureka Canvas - Sports Edition App - Lead/Sole iOS Developer

JAN 2022 - PRESENT

- Official App Store Release: https://apps.apple.com/us/app/eureka-canvas-sports-edition/id1643624044
- Developed a sport video markup app for a sports coach client.
- Integrated body position analysis code from Apple's 2020 WWDC Vision example.

- Full video scrolling/slider/ +/-5, play/pause, ½, ½, 1x, 2x buttons implemented.
- PencilKit API.
- StoreKit API for the app subscription.
- Custom shapes, arrows, and sports markup features.
- Ability to save and load canvases and game scenes.
- Use of trigonometry functions to calculate vector angles for shooting balls.
- Future updates will use Apple's Vision API to track the path of the ball from video analysis.

PlanetXR (https://www.planetxr.net/) - Lead iOS Developer

AUG 2022 - PRESENT

- https://apps.apple.com/us/app/planet-xr-1-spatial-ar-world/id16055046
 34
- Created a transparent tutorial video overlay on the main app screen.
- Timed UI text to coordinate with the transparent video.
- Used the view alpha channel to fade the tutorial and text in and out for a cinematic effect.
- Coded app logic to display the tutorial only in applicable scenarios.
- Updated the Google Maps view to display simultaneously with the AR camera in the bottom third of the screen to enhance the user's ability to find objects in the AR world while navigating in AR.
- Updated the map view system to include AR models and AR "air messages" based on their thumbnail or text data.
- Enabled map view for all users, not just developers in debug mode.
- Use of Jira system for software project management

WeatherSats AR, NASA/Andrew Morgan Consulting - Unity/C# Developer

MAY 2022 - PRESENT

- You can download this app on the App Store at the following URL: https://apps.apple.com/us/app/nasa-weathersats-ar/id6444034201
- Google Play Store link:
 <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.JPSS.WeatherSatsAR&hl=en_US&gl=US&g
- Added the AR models to the app and coded object manipulation scripts.
- Added and enhanced the AR features
- Built UI and UI behavior for the AR side of the app. (App has both AR and 3-D sections)
- Added additional UI features.
- Bug-fixed the AR and 3D systems and scene loader.
- PlasticSCM source control and Azure DevOps.
- Provided video updates to NASA of app development progress.
- Prepared and delivered the app to NASA for publishing on both the Google Play Store and App Store.
- App will become an exhibit at Goddard Space Flight Center in Maryland.

Upwork - Freelance iOS Developer/Freelance Unity Developer

JAN 2022 - PRESENT

- TrackHero (https://trackhero.com/), iOS Consultant
 - Served as a consultant to help the client make API calls using Combine.

- Implementation of the Stripe Purchase API
- Helped solve issues with concurrency, loading data models, and SwiftUI view management.
- Arrows Video Game, Sole Unity Developer
 - A Unity/C# WebGL third-person shooter game for a client called "Arrows."
 - You can play this game here: https://play.unity.com/mg/other/webgl builds-154388
- LEGO Sky Island Escape (Unity Port)
 - o I made a port of a Unity-based LEGO game to iOS.
 - I coded the user control logic and combined pre-built game levels, customizing some of the game levels.
 - Public beta is open through TestFlight here: https://testflight.apple.com/join/BDWu8n5P.

Craft - the Social Beer App - Sole iOS Developer

JAN 2019 - PRESENT

- o Founder of a Craft Beer social media startup with my brothers.
- App began as an extension of the MessageKit API, which allowed users to send messages and save their profile. Created 2019-2020.
- I used Firebase SDK for app user data, beer data, brewery data, beer cellar data, message data, and user authorization.
- o Facebook and Google login code integrated.
- o Custom emoji actions developed.
- App is now undergoing a SwiftUI overhaul. Overhaul is in its beginning stages.
- You can view my work and subscribe to this app via TestFlight at the following link: https://testflight.apple.com/join/oD1klg3sj.

OTHER EMPLOYMENT

Music Educator, Sept 2007 - Present

- Pequannock Board of Education/Pequannock, NJ
- Full-time elementary school general music teacher in the Pequannock school district.
- Band director, choir director

Bandleader, Hank Lane Music - Feb 2012 - Jan 2022

- Led a full-service wedding band for a leading entertainment company.
- Master of ceremonies, musical director, and client liaison for over 50 wedding events per year during my tenure.

SKILLS

- Swift
- C#
- Objective-C

- JavaScript
- SwiftUI
- UlKit

- Unity
- Firebase
- StoreKit
- AVKit
- MessageKit
- MapKit

- PencilKit
- React
- Bootstrap
- CSS
- HTML
- Game Development

EDUCATION

Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ - Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, Bachelor of Arts, Music

SEPT 2000 - MAY 2004

- Graduation from the Honors Program
- 4.0 GPA In Computer Science courses

CERTIFICATIONS

Introduction to Front-End Development, Coursera

AUG 2022

- Credential ID:WQ3JRSV5GD8G
- Credential URL:

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/WQ 3JRSV5GD8G

Unity Essentials Pathway, Unity Technologies

JAN 2021

Credential URL:

https://www.credly.com/badges/ab4e6d89-f757-443b-988e-583492d9dac4

AWARDS

- 772 Coding Score, CodeSignal
- CodeSignal, Level 42
- Linkedin Swift Badge

PORTFOLIO

- WeatherSats AR (NASA)
 - App Store:
 https://apps.apple.com/us/app/nasa-weathersats-ar/id6444034

201

Google Play Store:

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.JPSS.WeathersatsAR&hl=en_US&gl=US

- SoulandForm (SwiftUI/Swift/StoreKit/Firebase):
 - https://apps.apple.com/us/app/soul-and-form/id163
 3902006
- Eureka Canvas (SwiftUI/Swift/StoreKit):
 - https://apps.apple.com/us/app/eureka-canvas-sports-edition/id1643624044
- PlanetX AR (https://www.planetxr.net/)
- Craft the Social Beer App (UIKit/Swift/Firebase):
 - https://testflight.apple.com/join/qx30hlwj
- LEGO Sky Island Escape (iOS/Unity/C#):
 - https://testflight.apple.com/join/BDWu8n5P
- Arrows (Unity/C#/WebGL):
 - https://play.unity.com/mg/other/webgl-builds-154388